<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="https://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>Jepio's blog</title><link href="//jepio.github.io/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="//jepio.github.io/feeds/technology.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>//jepio.github.io/</id><updated>2015-05-29T21:23:00+02:00</updated><entry><title>Finally a new laptop</title><link href="//jepio.github.io/finally-a-new-laptop.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2015-05-29T21:23:00+02:00</updated><author><name>Jepio</name></author><id>tag:jepio.github.io,2015-05-29:finally-a-new-laptop.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;The time of my old laptop has come, it has finally died on me under mysterious
circumstances&lt;sup id="fnref:1"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:1" rel="footnote"&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;. It was a Samsung R530, with a T4400 2.2 GHz dual core
processor. Since I use &lt;a href="https://www.gentoo.org"&gt;gentoo&lt;/a&gt; most of the time I have to compile
(almost) all of my packages from source, which is very demanding on the
processor. I did not know unsuitable my old laptop was for this task until
this weeks.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have now purchased a Thinkpad T440s, with i5-4210U with a 1.7 GHz dual core
processor. But this time, it comes with turbo boost up to 2.7 GHz - though I
mostly see about 2.4 GHz on the clock - and hyperthreading. I have known about
hyperthreading for a while and because I know how it works (time slicing) I
didn't think it was particularly exciting. I couldn't have been more wrong. It
turns out that compiling is a sufficiently I/O heavy operation, that it can make
reasonable usage of the hyperthreading capabilities in the processor and get a
close to 2x boost compared to the 2 physical cores. Here's a couple of packages
whose compile times can be compared:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;table&gt;
&lt;thead&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;th&gt;package&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;time samsung&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;time thinkpad&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/thead&gt;
&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;llvm-3.6&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1 hour&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;37 minutes&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;gcc-4.9.2&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1 hour 40 min.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;36 min.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;boost-1.56&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;57 min.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;10 min.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now, I must admit that the comparison for boost is probably not fair - in one
case I built the static as well as the dynamic lib versions, and in the other
only the dynamic libs. But the speedup is amazing nonetheless.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It also seems that the Thinkpad has much better Linux support in general. I
tested Fedora 22 and everything ACPI related worked out of the box. On Gentoo
everything works - except for the microphone. The mic mute LED turns on at
udev device enumeration during init and stays on, I can't get it to work.
Anyone else experienced this? If so write me because I still haven't found a
solution.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="footnote"&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:1"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Not really... but let's not get into the details.&amp;#160;&lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:1" rev="footnote" title="Jump back to footnote 1 in the text"&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</summary></entry></feed>